According to a particular doctor,
there's a green powder that you can add
to your coffee that supercharges your
fat loss by 600%
or more. Welcome to the Centrifuge,
where we apply studies to verify or
debunk health shows. I'm talking about
Dr. Living Good, who every time I read
his name, I think to myself, it sounds
like the title to a 1980s song of some
sort instead of Dr. Feelgood by Mley
Crew. We're talking about Dr. Living
Good.
Anyway, Dr. Living Good is a doctor of
natural medicine and holds a doctorate
of chiropractic according to his website
and is also an Amazon best-selling
author. That said, in this episode of
Theuge, the main claims made by Dr.
living good are the addition of a green
powder called moringa to coffee causes
six times more body fat loss. Molecules
called isothiocyanates
that's going to be tough to say block
liver release of glucose thereby helping
with fat loss. And these same molecules,
isothiocyanates,
speed up fat release from the liver and
slow the speed at which fat cells are
produced, reducing future fat gain. And
there are timestamps for you to skip and
a recap of the most important points at
the end. Without further ado, let's spin
it. The final upgrade. Let's talk about
a plant that many nutrition researchers
consider one of the most nutrient-dense
foods on the planet. Gram for gram, it
contains far higher levels of certain
nutrients than many of the foods that we
eat every single day. Analysises of its
leaves have identified more than 90
different nutrients, 46 antioxidant
compounds, and because of this, the
plant is often called the miracle tree.
Talking about moringa. What made
researchers start paying attention to
moringa wasn't just the nutrition. It
was the results they started seeing in
weight loss studies. In one clinical
trial lasting 16 weeks, participants
lost as much as 2 to six times more
weight than the placebo groups, even
when diet and exercise were similar.
>> The main claim here is that moringa
coffee made people lose six times more
body weight than placebo, the
non-maringa coffee consuming group. In
the full content, which I'll link below,
Dr. living good describes this as the
most potent of six different coffee
additives for getting rid of body weight
potently. So he mentions some impressive
sounding information like 90 different
nutrients and 40 plus antioxidants. And
it is true that moringa is full of those
nutrients. The punchier and more
applicable aspect is the massive body
weight loss from consuming moringa
coffee compared to a group of people who
didn't consume the coffee. Now, as is
often the case, there were no citations
provided except for this graph, which
certainly looks incredible. The moringa
coffee clearly indicates huge
improvements not seen in the placebo.
However, with no citations for the
study, I can also create a graph that
looks impressive. Those who watched more
physionic videos were more miserable
than those who did not. Oh, wrong graph.
Uh, this one is what I meant. Those who
ate state fair fried alligator balls
gained 1,000%
more muscle than the placebo group. Now,
I'm poking a bit of fun, but truly, if
you mention study results, you should
probably cite it. That said, I think
that I was able to track down the study
because there aren't many studies on
moringa in people compared to a placebo
looking at weight loss over exactly 16
weeks. So knowing those clues, we find
only one study, this one. And sure
enough, looking at the data from the
study here, which I've transformed as a
graph here, we can see that it is true.
The moringa containing condition did
have much more weight loss and likely
fat loss. However, if you'll notice the
difference, the graphs are similar, but
there is no moringa coffee used in this
study. The intervention called LI85008F
contained moringa but not in coffee form
and also importantly not in isolation.
So the claim that moringa is the reason
for this increased weight loss is
premature as the study cited does not
isolate moringa. So therefore we can't
attribute the effects to moringa. I'd
like to return to this because there are
some moringa isolated studies I'd like
to lean on later that get us to a real
answer. For now, that has to be our
conclusion. There are, however, three
ways that moringa promotes fat loss.
Let's get into those. Results like that
made scientists start looking much more
closely at how this supplant affects the
metabolism. Turns out, moringa works
through several fat loss pathways all at
the same time. Your liver naturally
releases sugar into the bloodstream in
between meals. That's going to block fat
loss. But the isofothiocyanates
in moringa can block that sugar
production by as much as 60%.
>> The claim here is that the molecules
found inside moringa called
isothiocyanates
block the liver from releasing sugar
into the blood which would otherwise
block fat loss. The mechanism that Dr.
Living good I promise I'll stop is
describing is definitely plausible. It's
true that our liver releases glucose or
sugar molecules when prompted, like
during fasting periods. It's not quite
as simple as describing this release of
sugar as blocking fat loss, though. For
example, this sugar release happens
during fasting. But when we measure fat
metabolism, so fat metabolism tends to
be increased during fasting. So, while
I'd argue there's some truth, there's a
lot more to the scenario than described.
In fact, studies indicate that a rebound
in fat metabolism just a few hours after
eating, right in that window being
discussed. The point here being that
this mechanism is unlikely to be a big
player in affecting fat metabolism.
Regardless, do isothiocyanates
reduce the liver's production of
glucose? The answer is actually yes.
Again, no citations for the 60%
reduction, but this study indicates that
to be exactly right. Shown here, the
tall bar is on the left is the control
condition. So, normal production of
glucose by the liver, and the MC
conditions are the moringa with the
isothiocyanates.
Clearly, there's a huge decrease. And in
fact, it is exactly 60% if not more. So
it should probably be pointed out though
since we're you know kind of seamlessly
moving from human data to these data
that these data are in cell experiments
and animal experiments. So the direct
translation of 60% is unlikely. Still
mechanistically we should agree with Dr.
Livein good that isothiocyanates
from the moringa do reduce liver
production of glucose though the exact
amount of the effect in humans is
unknown. Now for the final two benefits
of isothiocyanates.
Second, those same compounds appear to
help break down stored fat faster. And
third, moringa seems to actually slow
the creation of new fat cells. In other
words, it doesn't just help burn fat, it
could also make it harder for your body
to store new fat in the first place. The
claims are that these same isothycinates
speed up fat release from the liver and
slow down new fat cells from being
created. Now, there are no human studies
that I could find that corroborate these
points, but the mouse study that we
looked at earlier does offer some signs
of reduced liver fat when exposed to
moringa shown here. The smaller the bar
that we're measuring liver fat is the
moringa condition. As for blocking or
slowing the production of new fat cells,
there's also evidence for that. However,
again, even more so than the last study,
we're talking about cell studies, so not
in humans and not even in another
greater organism. So, yeah, we can say
that moringa may help purge the liver of
fat and it may slow the formation of new
fat cells, but all the evidence is in
the earliest stages of research, not
clinical. Look, ultimately, we still
have the most outstanding question. Does
moringa lead to these sizable weight and
fat losses? I think you'll be surprised
by the results, but you won't be
surprised to know that I have a deeper
analysis of these studies that we've
been going over, including another study
that uses a completely different set of
molecules and has better evidence for
its effectiveness in coffee. If you're
interested in the more expansive full
version of this analysis that you're
watching, then check out the Physionic
Insiders. It's my premium research
platform which includes an article, a
one paragraph summary of the biggest
takeaways, a private podcast, live
sessions with me if you can tolerate it,
a supplement guide with approved
supplements, and much more. If you're
interested, check out the insiders using
the link in the description. Now, we had
one study cited, this one, but believe
it or not, there are several other
studies on the topic. Unlike the cited
study which combined many different
ingredients, these studies use only
moringa, therefore isolating the
effects. Unfortunately, there's no clear
effect because some of the studies
indicate a small weight loss effect and
indicate and some indicate no effect.
So, it's not only calls into question if
moringa is the real reason for this
super result that we saw in Dr. Living
Good's graph or if one of the other
ingredients was the bigger driver. In
the end, this is how I'd take the
current data across multiple studies
that are more appropriate to evaluate
moringa. There's either no effect or a
mild weight loss effect of moringa. I
think Dr. Living Good should have used
more appropriate studies instead of
focusing on the one study that showed
the greatest effect yet is impossible to
pin to moringa. I'd also point out that
adding a graph that says moringa coffee
and then exactly zero studies looked at
moringa coffee is misleading is a
classic case of cherrypicking and poor
communication. Not that it isn't clear,
it's just clearly wrong. That said, the
mechanisms hold some truth to them. And
when we refocus on the other studies
isolating moringa directly, what are
more appropriate conclusions? Well, for
one, moringa most definitely does not
lead to six times more body fat and
weight loss, but it could yield a mild
weight loss result in the best case
scenario. Moringa may work through
mechanisms outlined, so like the
increased fat release from the liver, uh
blocking the liver from producing sugar
that spills into the blood and so on.
But these mechanisms are completely
based on early incomplete evidence. So,
if you're interested in more centerfuge
episodes, then check them out right
here. And I suppose that just leaves me
with one last thing.
Dr. Living Good. If only Moringa would
hit it, Johnny.
See you next time.